Preliminary Guide to the Department of Education Records, 1930-1981 UA.25.18.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of Education records
1930 - 1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Dept. of Education
UA.25.18.0001
25 Linear Feet
The Department of Education, formed in 1907, prepared both undergraduate and graduate students for careers in education. The Department dissolved at the end of 1981. The Department of Education Records include correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, proposals, exams, student and faculty information, and other materials. Subjects include the training of teachers in North Carolina, the process of accreditation, teaching in elementary and secondary schools, and departmental administration. Major programs and organizations include the Master of Arts in Teaching Program, the Cooperative Program in Teacher Education, the N.C. Advancement School, the Triple T Task Force Team, the Emotionally Disturbed Children Program, the Regional Education Laboratory, the Learning Institute of North Carolina (LINC), the Durham Education Improvement Program (EIP), the Summer Demonstration School, the Summer Enrichment Program, and Project ABC. English.
25000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Department of Education Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1978 (A78-152), 1975 (A75-162), and 1998 (A98-60). Other accessions, including those in 1972 (A72-49), 1976 (A76-116), 1980 (A80-226), and 1981 (A81-39) have been interfiled.
Historical Note
By the charter of 1851, graduates of Normal College (the precursor to Trinity College) were recognized by the North Carolina legislature as qualified to teach in the common schools of the state. In 1859, President Braxton Craven introduced a teacher training curriculum. The Department of Education was formed at Trinity College in 1907, and teacher training programs, particularly those offered during the summer, enrolled many students. Prior to 1952, most students preparing to teach in the secondary schools majored in education. During the 1950s, this began to change; students could major in the subject they planned to teach, and be advised by members of the Department of Education. In 1954, a program leading to the degree of Master of Arts in Teaching was started, and throughout the 1950s, a number of special and cooperative programs were established. The 1960s saw an increase in the number of students seeking graduate training. By the late 1970s, the number of undergraduates intending to teach had begun to decline. The department was eliminated December 31, 1981 and replaced by a Program in Education in the College of Arts and Sciences, which enables undergraduates to meet state certification requirements. The Master of Arts in Teaching Degree continues to be offered.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, newsletters, grant proposals, accreditation studies, and other materials concerning teacher education at Duke. The collection includes program accreditation reports, examinations, reports of state studies on guidelines for teacher education records of the University Committee on Public Education and the Training of Teachers (1964-1974, scattered), conference announcements (1952, 1962), grant proposals for teacher recruitment and training programs, and materials concerning the 1952 Centennial Celebration of Teacher Education at Duke. Topics include general departmental operations, the Master's Degree in Education and Master of Arts in Teaching, the Summer Demonstration School, the Summer Enrichment Program (1974-1976), the Cooperative Program in Teacher Education, and Project ABC. Includes student records.
Related Material
Program in Education Records
Duke University Archives
Accreditation (Education); Elementary school teaching; High school teaching; Teachers -- Training of -- North Carolina; Duke University. Dept. of Education; Duke University. Dept. of Education; Regional Education Laboratories -- United States; North Carolina Advancement School
- Accession Number: A78-152
  - Includes correspondence of administrators, faculty, and students; course descriptions; student evaluations; information on admissions and enrollment; and other administrative materials, 1938-1953 (Box 1)
  - Includes information about hiring and personnel; correspondence and information on the Masters of Arts in Teaching programs at Duke and other schools; minutes and other materials related to departmental meetings; and information on Duke's Doctor of Education degree, 1952-1964 (Box 2)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't in Box 3), 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Minutes of departmental meetings, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't in Box 4), 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't from Box 3), 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't in Box 5), 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't from Box 4), 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Files of the Cooperative Program in Teacher Education (con't in Box 6), 1959-1964 (Box 5)
  - Files of the Cooperative Program in Teacher Education (con't from Box 5), 1959-1964 (Box 6)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files, 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't in Box 7), 1960-1961 (Box 6)
  - Departmental subject and correspondence files (con't from Box 6), 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - Departmental job applications - RESTRICTED, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - Files on the Cooperative Program in Teacher Education and Master of Arts in Teaching, approximately 1965-1974 (Box 7)
  - Departmental Records (arranged by subject), 1961-1963 (Box 7)
  - Departmental Records (arranged by subject), 1962-1964 (Box 8)
  - Department of Undergraduate Studies materials, 1962-1970 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and departmental records, [1960s] (Box 8)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, committees, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1963-1964 (Box 9)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1964-1965 (Box 9)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1966-1967 (Box 9)
  - Faculty Files, [1950s-1960s] - RESTRICTED (Box 10)
  - Departmental minutes, 1950-1967 (Box 10)
  - N.C. Advancement School, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Triple T Task Force Team, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1965-1969 (Box 11)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1970-1971 (Box 12)
  - Faculty Files, [1950s-1960s] - RESTRICTED (Box 12)
  - Departmental Records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), 1971-1974 (Box 13)
  - Files on the Emotionally Disturbed Children Program, 1963-1967 (Box 14)
  - Files on the Regional Education Laboratory, 1965-1966 (Box 14)
  - Files on the Learning Institute of North Carolina (LINC), 1964-1966 (Box 14)
  - Files on the Durham Education Improvement Program (EIP), 1964-1969 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous departmental records on organizations, administrative matters, and curriculum (arranged by subject), [1940s-1960s] (Box 15)
- Accession number A75-162
  - Files on Master of Arts in Teaching program, [late 1960s] (Box 16)
  - Correspondence of the Education Placement Bureau, 1930 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous departmental records on administrative matters and curriculum (arranged by subject), [1960s-1980] (Box 16)
  - Exams and correspondence related to the Masters of Arts in Teaching program - RESTRICTED, [1940s] (Box 17)
- Accession number: A98-60
  - Chronological files of departmental minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other records, 1957-1981 (Box 18)
  - Reports on Teacher Education at Duke University, 1969-1979 (Box 18)